<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-28T21:43:14+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">May Helena Plumb</title><subtitle>May Helena Plumb is a linguist who studies Zapotec languages.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">These are a few of my favorite things about Oaxaca</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/07/02/my-favorite-things-about-Oaxaca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="These are a few of my favorite things about Oaxaca" /><published>2019-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/07/02/my-favorite-things-about-Oaxaca</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/07/02/my-favorite-things-about-Oaxaca/">&lt;p&gt;I’m home in Austin now. My 2019 fieldwork is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fieldwork is complicated for me, as I imagine it is for many researchers. It is simultaneously the best part of my job and the most stressful. Research in the field is hard, and by the end I’m mentally exhausted. Traveling is hard for me, and usually after a month I’m emotionally exhausted. But overall, spending time in Oaxaca is one of the greatest blessings of my life (I wouldn’t do it if it didn’t make me happy). This post is a collection of things I love about Oaxaca, drafted slowly over the past five weeks.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love saying &lt;i&gt;buenos días&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;buenas tardes&lt;/i&gt; to people in the street, even if I still feel a bit awkward and half the time I get the time of day wrong.  I love also how eventually I start becoming more attuned to the patterns of the church bells, so that I can tell when it’s past noon (and therefore &lt;i&gt;buenas tardes&lt;/i&gt; is the appropriate greeting). With each trip to Oaxaca, I start feeling a little more comfortable, a little more at home. Learning the patterns of the town is a big part of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;After like a week I realized that the Tlacochahuaya church plays Ave Maria at noon, so that&amp;#39;s how people know at 12:02 that you&amp;#39;re supposed to say buenas tardes&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&amp;#39;ve slowly become more accustomed to hearing the various bells that signal different things in town [2/3]&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; May Helena Plumb (@mayhplumb) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mayhplumb/status/1140718542758862848?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 17, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love studying Zapotec. While I’m in Oaxaca, I get to spend all my hours thinking about language. There’s nothing else I’m supposed to be doing — not classwork or grading or renewing my drivers’ license, just delving into whatever aspect of Zapotec grammar excites me most. Not that it’s always easy. Some days I wrestle with the language. But other days I dance with it. Exploring the maze of language (and meeting people along the way) is constant source of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love being close to nature. Most houses in Tlacochahuaya are organized as individual rooms that open onto a courtyard. It reminds me of my childhood, when I spent far more time outside and far less time in climate-controlled rooms. In Oaxaca, I get hear the rain, the wind, the thunder. I get to smell the dirt. I get to feel the chilled breeze of a coming storm. I sit in my bedroom doorway and watch the birds and the lizards. (I also scratch mosquito bites, which is significantly less pleasant.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;On the other hand, when I&amp;#39;m safely inside my room and the rain starts to pour, it is virtually impossible for me to work because I&amp;#39;m so distracted&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I just wanna watch the storm! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/jyHP1JzRAJ&quot;&gt;https://t.co/jyHP1JzRAJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; May Helena Plumb (@mayhplumb) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mayhplumb/status/1135698509011832832?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 4, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the noise. Well, sometimes. If you ask me about it when I’m tired, when the roosters and the fireworks and the car alarms and the donkeys and the loudspeaker announcements all chime in together, with someone’s radio playing pop music a few doors down and the neighborhood dogs shouting their warnings to each other in the street… well, I might not have a very rosy attitude about the noise. But at the same time, I love it. Because noise is part of Oaxaca, and I love Oaxaca.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at its core, that’s just how fieldwork is. It’s intense — sensorially, emotionally, academically. There is so much to take in, so much to do, so many new things vying for your attention in every moment. Fieldwork is &lt;i&gt;overwhelming&lt;/i&gt;, in every way, and that can be painful. But when I’m squashed into a collective taxi with six people and a turkey and a love song on the radio, and I’m watching the sun illuminate the distant mountains, I am mainly overwhelmed with happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close, let me offer some thanks. I am grateful to Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, who introduced me to Oaxaca and to Zapotec. I am grateful to other mentors who have supported my research over the years, including George Aaron Broadwell and Anthony C. Woodbury.  I thank the Tlacochahuaya 2016-2019 town council for their support of my project. And of course, my deepest gratitude goes to my Zapotec teachers, in particular Moisés García Guzmán, who housed me, fed me, and so graciously shared his language with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research in Tlacochahuaya has been funded by the Carlota Smith Fellowship (UT Austin; 2019), the Donald D. Harrington Graduate Fellowship (UT Austin; 2018, 2019), the Sherzer Research Fund (UT Austin; 2018), NSF REU Site Grant #1461056 (2015, 2016),&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;PI Harrison, &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Building Digital Tools to Support Endangered Languages and Preserve Environmental Knowledge in Mexico, Micronesia, and Navajo Nation&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the Louis Greene Fund (Haverford College; 2017), and the Center for Peace and Global Citizenship (Haverford College, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">I’m home in Austin now. My 2019 fieldwork is complete. Fieldwork is complicated for me, as I imagine it is for many researchers. It is simultaneously the best part of my job and the most stressful. Research in the field is hard, and by the end I’m mentally exhausted. Traveling is hard for me, and usually after a month I’m emotionally exhausted. But overall, spending time in Oaxaca is one of the greatest blessings of my life (I wouldn’t do it if it didn’t make me happy). This post is a collection of things I love about Oaxaca, drafted slowly over the past five weeks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What do we mean by “present” tense</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/25/what-do-we-mean-by-present/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What do we mean by &quot;present&quot; tense" /><published>2019-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/25/what-do-we-mean-by-present</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/25/what-do-we-mean-by-present/">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;#prelim-research&quot;&gt;Disclaimer: This is preliminary research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;collapse&quot; id=&quot;prelim-research&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p class=&quot;card card-body&quot; style=&quot;padding: 2mm; margin-bottom: 3mm;&quot;&gt;
				Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me.
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, the “tense” of a verb (which I’m actually going to call the “TAM”&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;It stands for 'tense, aspect, and mood'. You can check out the &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tense%E2%80%93aspect%E2%80%93mood'&amp;gt;Wikipedia page&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; to learn more, or see &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://youtu.be/VM8GlP6avF4'&amp;gt;this video&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; for a discussion of the difference between tense and aspect&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) is indicated by a prefix, for example ‘Juan talks’ is &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;r&lt;/b&gt;ni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; with &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; at the beginning, while ‘Juan is talking’ is &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;ka&lt;/b&gt;ni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; with the prefix &lt;i&gt;ka-&lt;/i&gt;. In a &lt;a title=&quot;Studying Tlacochahuaya Zapotec 'tense'&quot; href=&quot;/blog/2019/06/04/tlacochahuaya-zapotec-tam/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I looked at how verbs are divided into categories based on which TAM prefixes they use for “past” and “future”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently in my research, I’ve been focusing on that &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; prefix in &lt;i&gt;rni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; ‘Juan talks’.  I want to figure out what the &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; means, which is a harder question that it might sound!&lt;!--excerpt--&gt; TAM (“tense”) in the world’s languages is often very complex in meaning. For example, the English “present tense” (&lt;i&gt;eats&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;sits&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;hugs&lt;/i&gt;) usually indicates that an action is a habit/custom. That is, &lt;i&gt;Ellen eats meat&lt;/i&gt; means that Ellen is in the habit of eating meat (but she might not be eating meat right now). However, sports announcers also use the “present tense” form to talk about an event that is happening right this instant (&lt;i&gt;She shoots, she scores!&lt;/i&gt;). Furthermore, you can use the same “present tense” to make a story seem more immediate and exciting, even if the events you’re talking about happened in the past (&lt;i&gt;So I ask them to pass the salt, and they say…&lt;/i&gt;).  So in English, we use this “present tense” to mean many different things! Likewise, I want to know all the ways that you can use the Tlacochahuaya Zapotec &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; prefix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When other researchers have described Zapotec languages, they usually call the &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; prefix “habitual” because it’s prototypical use is to indicate a habitual/customary action. Like the English present! However, unlike the English present, the Zapotec habitual can also be used to talk about &lt;i&gt;past&lt;/i&gt; habitual actions (like English &lt;i&gt;used to&lt;/i&gt;). Depending on context, &lt;i&gt;rni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; could just as easily mean ‘Juan talks [all the time]’ or ‘Juan used to talk [all the time, e.g. when he was a child]’. The Zapotec habitual &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; contrasts with the prefix &lt;i&gt;ka-&lt;/i&gt;, which indicates that an action is in progress (we call it “progressive”). Like with &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;ka-&lt;/i&gt; can talk about the present or the past, so &lt;i&gt;kani Jwan&lt;/i&gt; can mean either ‘Juan is talking’ or ‘Juan was talking’.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;For those following along at home: 'Juan talks' in English is desribed as present tense, habitual aspect. 'Juan is talking' is described as present tense, progressive aspect.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, this seems pretty straight forward. Well, it is, until you ask someone how to say ‘the baby is sleeping’, and they say &lt;i&gt;ra’asy bdo&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;interlinear&quot;&gt;
	&lt;tr class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;&lt;td&gt;r-a'asy&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;bdo&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;R-sleep&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This is called an &amp;lt;span class='jargon'&amp;gt;interlinear gloss&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;. The idea is to label each part of each word with it's meaning. But since I don't really know what &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;r-&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; means yet, I'm just labelling it 'R'!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;baby&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;'The baby is sleeping.'&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that with the verb ‘sleep’, you usually don’t use the prefix &lt;i&gt;ka-&lt;/i&gt;. You just use &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; instead. There are a couple of other verbs like this, including ‘snore’ and ‘be hungry’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;interlinear&quot;&gt;
	&lt;tr class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;&lt;td&gt;r-ubikia&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;bëny&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;R-snore&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;person&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;'The person is snoring.'&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;interlinear&quot;&gt;
	&lt;tr class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;&lt;td&gt;r-ndyeny&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;be'ekw&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;R-be.hungry&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;dog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;'The dog is hungry.'&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a question I have right now is: which verbs exactly act like this? Is a fixed set of random verbs? Or is a category based on the type of action? I have a hypothesis I’m working with right now, but it’s too soon in the game to even post about it here!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="mays-qualifying-paper" /><category term="tense-aspect-mood" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">Disclaimer: This is preliminary research Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me. In Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, the “tense” of a verb (which I’m actually going to call the “TAM”) is indicated by a prefix, for example ‘Juan talks’ is rni Jwan with r- at the beginning, while ‘Juan is talking’ is kani Jwan with the prefix ka-. In a previous post, I looked at how verbs are divided into categories based on which TAM prefixes they use for “past” and “future”. Recently in my research, I’ve been focusing on that r- prefix in rni Jwan ‘Juan talks’. I want to figure out what the r- means, which is a harder question that it might sound!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A brief introduction to Tlacochahuaya Zapotec</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/18/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A brief introduction to Tlacochahuaya Zapotec" /><published>2019-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/18/intro-to-tlacochahuaya</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/18/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/">&lt;p&gt;San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya is located in the Tlacolula Valley in Oaxaca, Mexico. Tlacochahuaya is about 18 kilometers east of Oaxaca City, a 40-minute drive from the city’s historical center, and has around 2,300 inhabitants.  Like most towns in the area, there are three parts of Tlacochahuaya’s name. &lt;i&gt;San Jerónimo&lt;/i&gt; (Saint Jerome) is the patron saint of the town. &lt;i&gt;Tlacochahuaya&lt;/i&gt; is the town’s Nahuatl name, and the official name used by the state.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Nahuatl is the language of the Aztecs, and the Spanish colonizers adopted these names for many towns throughout Mexico, regardless of the indigenous group that lived there. In Nahuatl, &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Tlacochahuaya&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; means 'wet place', referring to the lake that used to be here.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And of course, Tlacochahuaya also has a Zapotec name: &lt;i&gt;Zunni ro’o&lt;/i&gt;.  Incidentally, the word &lt;i&gt;Zapotec&lt;/i&gt; also comes from Nahuatl. In Tlacochahuaya, they call Zapotec people &lt;i&gt;Bënza&lt;/i&gt;, and the language is &lt;i&gt;Dizhsa&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 1em;&quot;&gt;Click a word to hear it's pronunciation:&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for 'Bënza' on the Tlacochahuaya Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=3916&quot;&gt;Bënza&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;A recording of the word 'Nahuatl' on Wikipedia&quot; href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1e/Nawatl.ogg&quot;&gt;Nahuatl&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;A recording of me saying 'Oaxaca' (in my very gringa accent)&quot; href=&quot;/blog/files/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/oaxaca-pronunciation.mp3&quot;&gt;Oaxaca&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;A recording of me saying 'San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya' (in my very gringa accent)&quot; href=&quot;/blog/files/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/tlacochahuaya-pronunciation.mp3&quot;&gt;San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;A recording of me saying 'Tlacolula' (in my very gringa accent)&quot; href=&quot;/blog/files/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/tlacolula-pronunciation.mp3&quot;&gt;Tlacolula&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-md mt-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for 'Zunni ro'o' on the Tlacochahuaya Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=4092&quot;&gt;Zunni r'o&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col col-md-8 center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img alt=&quot;map of the Tlacolula Valley&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/intro-to-tlacochahuaya/tlacolula-valley.png&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Map of the Tlacolula Valley; San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya is marked in blue in the middle of the map.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This map is from a book called &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Oaxaca: Distritos, Limites, Caminos, Municipios, y Localidades&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;, published by Angel García García y Asociados, S.C. It has maps of different parts of Oaxaca, as well as census data for all the towns. Last I tried, you could buy a copy at Priv. De Rayón No. 104, Centro, Oax. 68000. Or &amp;lt;a href='mailto:mayhplumb@utexas.edu'&amp;gt;email me&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; if you'd like a scan of something. :)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;i&gt;Zapotec&lt;/i&gt; does not refer to a single language, but to a language family containing dozens of individual languages.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;It’s similar in diversity to the Romance language family, which includes French, Spanish, Romanian, Italian, Catalan, Aragonese…&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The Zapotec language family has a high level of dialect variation; in the Tlacolula Valley, every town speakers a slightly distinct variety of Zapotec. This forms what linguists call a “dialect chain”, where any two towns next to each other will be quite similar, but towns on opposite ends of the chain will speak very differently.  In this context, the difference between a “language” and a “dialect” is hard to define. Tlacochahuaya Zapotec is certainly its own variety within the Valley, but for example it has many similarities to the Zapotec spoken in San Lucas Quiaviní (near Tlacolula, which is marked in orange on the map above).&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;I’d also like to note that Oaxaca has a high level of linguistic diversity in general. Zapotec is one of many language families in the region, including Mixe, Otomi, Chatino, Mixtec, Zoque, and Chinantec. And each of these families contains several individual languages. There are hundreds of indigenous languages spoken in the state of Oaxaca!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec grammar is something I’ll expand upon in other posts (click &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tag/zapotec/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for all posts about Zapotec), but here are some basic facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Zapotec languages have Verb-Subject-Object word order. That means that while in English we say &lt;i&gt;Tomorrow, Juan will harvest corn&lt;/i&gt;, in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec you say &quot;Tomorrow, will harvest Juan corn&quot;.
        &lt;table class=&quot;interlinear&quot;&gt;
            &lt;tr class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;&lt;td&gt;zhí&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;í-ndá’á&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Jwany&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;gell&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;tomorrow&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;future-harvest&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Juan&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;corn&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr class=&quot;parts-of-speech&quot;&gt;&lt;td&gt;adverb&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;verb&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;subject&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;object&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;'Tomorrow, Juan will harvest corn'&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        Zapotec languages are tonal. This means that the pitch of a word can change what it means. So far, I've been able to identify four tones in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec: 
        1. low, as in &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for zhi'i on the Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=3902&quot;&gt;zhi'i&lt;/a&gt; 'nose'; 
        2. high, as in &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for zhí'í on the Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=3901&quot;&gt;zhí'í&lt;/a&gt; 'cold, flu'; 
        3. rising, as in &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for zhǐly on the Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=3419&quot;&gt;zhǐly&lt;/a&gt; 'sheep'; 
        and 4. falling, as in &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The entry for zhîly on the Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/?entry=3857&quot;&gt;zhîly&lt;/a&gt; 'cotton'.
        (Click the words to hear recordings on the Talking Dictionary.)
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;While English uses the passive construction to say things like &lt;i&gt;The money was counted&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;The plate was cleaned&lt;/i&gt;, Zapotec tends to have stand-alone intranstive verbs for these (&lt;i&gt;-gab&lt;/i&gt; 'get counted, &lt;i&gt;-ye&lt;/i&gt; 'get cleaned').&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec has six basic vowels: [i e a o u ɨ]. You can listen to these vowels using the phonetic alphabet guide &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ipachart.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;The sixth vowel [ɨ] is most difficult for English speakers to reproduce. To make it, you can start by make the vowel [i] as in &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;beet&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;. Then make the vowel [u] as in &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;boot&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;. Try going back and forth between these two vowels. Notice that in [i] the front of your tongue is raised up, and your lips are spread in a smile, while in [u] the back of your tongue is raised, and your lips are rounded. To make [ɨ], you should stop about half way between [i] and [u] (with the mid section of your tongue raised) and with your lips spread, not rounded.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, when it’s raining while the sun is shining (a sun shower), you say that a deer is being born, &lt;i&gt;kayal bzhëny&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tlacochahuaya, the youngest (fluent) speaker of Zapotec is in his early 40s. Because children are no longer learning the language — and because of the socioeconomic and cultural pressure of Spanish — linguists consider Tlacochahuaya Zapotec to be highly endangered. There are some towns in the Tlacolula Valley where Zapotec is still spoken by children, but this is very rare, partly because of discrimination against indigenous languages in schools. However, activists in Tlacochahuaya have started language workshops for both adults and children, which are generously supported by the local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? Follow this blog! And here are some other resources about Zapotec and Tlacochahuaya:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can hear more Tlacochahuaya Zapotec words on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/&quot;&gt;Talking Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Watch Dizhsa Nabani&quot; href=&quot;https://doculabs.haverford.edu/dizhsanabani/watch/&quot;&gt;Dizhsa Nabani&lt;/a&gt; is a beautiful documentary about language and daily life in Tlacochahuaya.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bddESEmsZTc&quot;&gt;this interview&lt;/a&gt;, Janet Chávez Santiago speaks about her personal experience facing discrimination in school for speaking Zapotec the neighboring town of Teotitlán del Valle (video in Spanish, with subtitles in English).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tlacochahuaya’s church is home to a beautiful historic organ. There's a video in Spanish &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DvNbr1w8HJM&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="language-documentation" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya is located in the Tlacolula Valley in Oaxaca, Mexico. Tlacochahuaya is about 18 kilometers east of Oaxaca City, a 40-minute drive from the city’s historical center, and has around 2,300 inhabitants. Like most towns in the area, there are three parts of Tlacochahuaya’s name. San Jerónimo (Saint Jerome) is the patron saint of the town. Tlacochahuaya is the town’s Nahuatl name, and the official name used by the state. And of course, Tlacochahuaya also has a Zapotec name: Zunni ro’o. Incidentally, the word Zapotec also comes from Nahuatl. In Tlacochahuaya, they call Zapotec people Bënza, and the language is Dizhsa.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons in fieldwork self-care</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/13/fieldwork-self-care/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons in fieldwork self-care" /><published>2019-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/13/fieldwork-self-care</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/13/fieldwork-self-care/">&lt;p&gt;This summer is my fifth research trip to Oaxaca, and over the years I’ve developed a few ways to remedy stress and homesickness.  To be clear, I love Oaxaca. It is a pleasure and a privilege to come here every year. But fieldwork is &lt;i&gt;hard&lt;/i&gt;, and because the essence of my research is so tied up in my daily life, I need to be really conscious about taking breaks and de-stressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my self-care is in the little things that I pack. I always bring some nail polish, because it encourages me to take little moments for myself. &lt;!--excerpt--&gt; My packing list also includes a craft project — I just finished knitting a pair of &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;My Ravelry project page for the socks&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ravelry.com/projects/mayhplumb/kalajoki&quot;&gt;socks&lt;/a&gt;, and my next project is a &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;My Ravelry project page for the shawl&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ravelry.com/projects/mayhplumb/early-blooms&quot;&gt;shawl&lt;/a&gt; — and some comfort books.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This year's books are &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Winnie-the-Pooh&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Adventures of Frog and Toad&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;. I usually like to bring something nostalgic that's easy to read in bits and pieces.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  A new addition to my packing list this year is nice mints. A friend introduced me to these excellent rose-flavored ones, and they’ve been very helpful for calming myself down when I get stressed out about my research process.  These are all small things that are easy to pack but make a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;These mints have been a lovely addition to my fieldwork self-care toolkit. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;They literally taste like a rose is blooming in your mouth. Prefect for when I need to pause &amp;amp; relax for a moment. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(Thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drwordperson?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@drwordperson&lt;/a&gt; for the recommendation!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/uW7TqVYfNs&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/uW7TqVYfNs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; May Helena Plumb (@mayhplumb) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mayhplumb/status/1135943102303260673?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 4, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key I’ve discovered is maintaining communication with friends and family. I make a point to tell my boyfriend about my accomplishments each day, no matter how small, because telling someone else makes them feel real.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;He's a reliable and energetic cheerleader, even on my rough days, and I'm incredibly grateful for it.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m also part of a WhatsApp group with all of the other students in my department doing fieldwork. We talk about our wins and loses, ask questions about research methods, share pictures of lizards, and generally support each other through the summer.  Another way I stay in contact is by playing Words with Friends with my mom! Obviously, consistent communication isn’t feasible for all people and all field sites. But for me, at this stage of my research and of my life, it’s important to maintain those connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the most important self-care strategies I’ve developed over the years are the ones that are specific to Oaxaca. While having reminders of home makes me feel comforted, it’s crucial to put some of my focus outward and to remember to take joy in my life here as well. One example: as a reward on a warm day, I get myself &lt;i&gt;nieve&lt;/i&gt; (somewhere between sorbet and Philly water ice) from one of the stands by the market.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;My favorite combination is &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;tuna&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (prickly pear fruit) with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;leche quemada&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; ('burnt milk'), which I have never encountered in the US.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It’s a special Oaxacan treat, and it never fails to remind me how lucky I am to visit this lovely place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-cards=&quot;hidden&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Since i) it&amp;#39;s warm out and ii) I succeeded at a thing today, I treated myself to un nieve de tuna con leche quemada&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(prickly pear fruit and &amp;quot;burnt milk&amp;quot; sorbet) &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/bf82HIps8K&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/bf82HIps8K&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; May Helena Plumb (@mayhplumb) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mayhplumb/status/1135960862706032641?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 4, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these strategies are not right for everyone. Self-care in the field — like self-care anywhere! — is a slow and steady process of figuring out what works for you. But I do think that in planning for fieldwork, it’s worth considering these three categories of self-care: small comfort items from home; social connection with loved ones; and local activities to keep you grounded.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="personal" /><category term="self-care" /><summary type="html">This summer is my fifth research trip to Oaxaca, and over the years I’ve developed a few ways to remedy stress and homesickness. To be clear, I love Oaxaca. It is a pleasure and a privilege to come here every year. But fieldwork is hard, and because the essence of my research is so tied up in my daily life, I need to be really conscious about taking breaks and de-stressing. Some of my self-care is in the little things that I pack. I always bring some nail polish, because it encourages me to take little moments for myself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early research on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec pronouns</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/11/tlacochahuaya-pronouns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early research on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec pronouns" /><published>2019-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/11/tlacochahuaya-pronouns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/11/tlacochahuaya-pronouns/">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;#prelim-research&quot;&gt;Disclaimer: This is preliminary research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;collapse&quot; id=&quot;prelim-research&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p class=&quot;card card-body&quot; style=&quot;padding: 2mm; margin-bottom: 3mm;&quot;&gt;
				Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me.
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things you learn when studying a language are the &lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;pronouns&lt;/span&gt; — the &lt;i&gt;it&lt;/i&gt;’s and &lt;i&gt;they&lt;/i&gt;’s and &lt;i&gt;we&lt;/i&gt;’s of a language. We use pronouns like variables, so that we can refer to different people and objects without using their full names.  &lt;i&gt;Some&lt;/i&gt; of the pronouns of English are shown below. For the purpose of this table, I chosen the pronouns that I use most frequently/naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;(Some of the) English pronouns&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;singular&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;plural&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;1st person&lt;/td&gt;                        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;I&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;we&lt;/td&gt;                 &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;2nd person&lt;/td&gt;                        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;you&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;you/y'all&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, feminine&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;she&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;they&lt;/td&gt;                 &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, masculine&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;he&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;they&lt;/td&gt;                 &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, neutral/agender&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;they&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;they&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, inanimate/nonhuman&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;it&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;it&lt;/td&gt;                 &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other pronouns in English: some dialects of English have &lt;i&gt;youse&lt;/i&gt; as a 2nd person plural, for example, and there are additional agender pronouns, like &lt;i&gt;zie&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;For information about agender pronouns and nonbinary folks generally, see these pages from: &amp;lt;a target=_'blank' href='https://uwm.edu/lgbtrc/support/gender-pronouns/'&amp;gt;the UWM LGBT Resource center&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://transequality.org/issues/resources/understanding-non-binary-people-how-to-be-respectful-and-supportive'&amp;gt;the National Center for Transgender Equality&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://www.them.us/story/inqueery-agender'&amp;gt;the online publication &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;them&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Furthermore, some of the pronouns in this list have other uses, such as the so-called “royal &lt;i&gt;we&lt;/i&gt;”, which is singular, not plural. While I’ve called &lt;i&gt;it&lt;/i&gt; the “3rd person, inanimate/nonhuman” form, we commonly give gendered animate pronouns to inanimate objects, like when we call boats&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Or if you're Jonathan Van Ness, anything!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;she&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pronoun system I’ve given for English is just one way of dividing up individuals into groups. But different languages have different sets of pronouns! Many languages have a distinction between formal and informal 2nd person pronouns, like Spanish &lt;i&gt;Usted&lt;/i&gt; vs. &lt;i&gt;tú&lt;/i&gt;.  So how does this play out in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec? Here’s the pronouns of the language as I currently understand them:&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This is &amp;lt;b&amp;gt;very preliminary research&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;, and I've simplified the spelling significantly, so please don't quote me on this!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec pronouns (spelling simplified)&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;singular&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;plural&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;1st person&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;nare&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;donn&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;2nd person, informal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;liu&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/td&gt;             &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;2nd person, formal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;gibyu&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;yubtë&lt;/td&gt;             &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, informal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lány&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladeny&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, formal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lab&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladep&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, reverent&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lany&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladény&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, masculine?&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lazh:&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladezh:&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, infant&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;laby&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladeby&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, animal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lam&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;ladem&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, inanimate&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;niñ&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;deniñ&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec has quite a few more pronouns than English does! In particular, they make many more distinctions in the third person. One pattern you might notice here is that all the third person plural pronouns include &amp;lt;de&amp;gt;. In fact, &lt;i&gt;de&lt;/i&gt; on it’s own is just a plural marker! So for example, &lt;i&gt;geht&lt;i&gt; means ‘tortilla’ and &lt;i&gt;de geht&lt;/i&gt; means ‘tortillas’.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For comparison, let’s look at pronouns from San Lucas Quiaviní, another Zapotec-speaking town, just a few kilometers away from Tlacochahuaya.  You’ll notice they look pretty different, even though the languages are so closely related!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec pronouns (based on Munro &amp;amp; Lopez's 1999 dictionary; spelling simplified)&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;singular&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;plural&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;1st person&lt;/td&gt;                        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;na&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;dannonn&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;2nd person, informal&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;liu&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lad&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;2nd person, formal&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;yu&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;yuad&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, informal, nearby&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lang&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;larëng&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, informal, far away&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lai&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lariny&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, respectful&lt;/td&gt;            &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lazh:&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;larazh:&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, reverent&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lainy&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lariny&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;3rd person, animal&lt;/td&gt;                &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;lamm&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;foreign&quot;&gt;larëmm&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key difference is that where Tlacochahuaya Zapotec has &amp;lt;de&amp;gt;, San Lucas Quiaviní has &amp;lt;r&amp;gt; or &amp;lt;rë&amp;gt;. Also, San Lucas Quiaviní has slightly different pronoun categories. For example, in this language, they distinguish between “nearby” and “far away” in the 3rd person informal. You might also notice that the San Lucas Quiaviní “respectful” pronoun, &lt;i&gt;lazh:&lt;/i&gt;, looks a lot like the Tlacochahuaya “masculine” pronoun, &lt;i&gt;lazh:&lt;/i&gt;.  The Tlacochahuaya version has been described to me as being only for men, but it could be it’s used more generally in practice — that’s something I’ll need to find out! Also, just like we often use human pronouns for boats in English, it’s likely that people can use Tlacochahuaya Zapotec pronouns outside of their “typical” categories.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;For example, in San Lucas Quiaviní, the &amp;quot;nearby&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;far away&amp;quot; categories may refer to either physical or psychological distance.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That’s something I’m on the lookout for when I’m translating Zapotec stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? You might have noticed that lots of people are talking about pronouns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For introductions, the linguistics podcast &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://lingthusiasm.com/post/156181768226/transcript-lingthusiasm-episode-2-pronouns&quot;&gt;Lingthusiasm&lt;/a&gt; and the YouTube channel &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fvohHpylRkY&quot;&gt;Ling Space&lt;/a&gt; both have episodes about pronouns.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;There are many linguists who specifically research pronouns and gender. As just two examples, I highly recommend work by Kirby Conrod (see &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Kirby's website&quot; href=&quot;https://kconrod.herokuapp.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Kirby's medium post about gender and linguistics&quot; href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kconrod/lsa-2019-trans-itive-gendering-fb9c3a7bc2d1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and Lauren Ackerman (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Lauren's page about pronouns and gender research&quot; href=&quot;https://lmackerman.com/pronouns-and-gender/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For some more technical reading material about Zapotec pronouns, check out &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1086/379683&quot;&gt;Operstein's &quot;Personal pronouns in Zapotec and Zapotecan&quot;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.questia.com/library/journal/1G1-92404218/hierarchical-pronouns-in-discourse-third-person-pronouns&quot;&gt;Munro's &quot;Hierarchical pronouns in discourse&quot;&lt;/a&gt; (Unfortunately both are paywalled, but let me know if you want a copy.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="pronouns" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">Disclaimer: This is preliminary research Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me. One of the first things you learn when studying a language are the pronouns — the it’s and they’s and we’s of a language. We use pronouns like variables, so that we can refer to different people and objects without using their full names. Some of the pronouns of English are shown below. For the purpose of this table, I chosen the pronouns that I use most frequently/naturally. (Some of the) English pronouns singular plural 1st person I we 2nd person you you/y'all 3rd person, feminine she they 3rd person, masculine he they 3rd person, neutral/agender they they 3rd person, inanimate/nonhuman it it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metadata: Hundreds of recordings, but what are they about?</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/06/metadata/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metadata: Hundreds of recordings, but what are they about?" /><published>2019-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/06/metadata</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/06/metadata/">&lt;p&gt;At the end of each day of fieldwork, I sit down and “deal with my data”. No matter how tired I am, no matter how much I want to put it off, it’s an essential part of my daily routine. The first thing I do is back up my recordings.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;I keep lots of copies of my recordings, in case one copy gets lost or damaged. (1) I keep the original SD cards. (2) I back up the SD cards to an external drive. (3) I move key files to a separate external drive, where they're organized by topic. (4) I slowly (pending wifi) move those key files to Dropbox. This might be excessive, but better safe than sorry.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And while my files are transferring, I go over my notes and make sure that all of my &lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt; is in order. Metadata is all the information about how the recording was made — who was there, where we were, what we talked about, what audio recorder I used, etc. Metadata is &lt;i&gt;data about data&lt;/i&gt;, and it’s a crucial aspect of good data management.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proper metadata serves many roles. For me as a researcher, it means I can always identify which handwritten notes go with which recordings, and I can remember which person told me what when. But more importantly, when I archive my data, metadata makes the resources more accessible to other researchers. Ideally, when some future linguist looks at my recordings, they’ll be able to reconstruct the research context and methodology. This means they can properly interpret what the data means and how it should be analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my practice, I record metadata in three ways. First, at the start of each session, I record relevant information in my field notebook. My metadata for my first research session this summer looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-10 center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;mx-auto d-block img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;One page one of a notebook, there's the following text: 'May HP (Researcher), Moises GG (Speaker), June 1, 2019, SJTZ, San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya, Archive + CC = YES, Zoom H5 w/ XYH5 mic + Shure headset, SD005, Multi, Folder01, Zoom01, 190601-200918. Below the metdata you can see the first notes, the word 'dig' in a box, with the Zapotec 'gal rga'an' and the note '(infinitive/nomlz)'.&quot; title=&quot;I feel very vulnerable showing this to other people. Even though I know I'll archive it eventually, it feels so personal!&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/metadata/notebook-metadata.jpg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;May Helena Plumb, NB005, page 1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of information here! First I’ve noted the two people involved in this research session, me (MayHP), and Moisés García Guzmán; at the end of the notebook, I include a list of name abbreviations and brief biographical sketches.  I also note the date, and the language being documented. In this case, the language is San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, which I abbreviate “SJTZ” (again, there’s a list of language abbreviations at the back of the book).  I also include the town we were working, and I note whether Moisés gave permission for me to archive this material publicly.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;CC stands for &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='The Creative Commons website' href='https://creativecommons.org/'&amp;gt;Creative Commons&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and I've specified the CC &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='License page for CC BY-SA' href='https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/'&amp;gt;Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;... at the back of the notebook.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  I recorded this session, so I also note information about the recording, including the audio recorder and microphones I used,&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;A Zoom H5 Handy Recorder with the XYH-5 onboard mic, and a Shure SM10A-CN, which is a headset with a cardioid mic.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the SD card where the file was recorded.  There’s more information about the recording equipment — you guessed it — at the back of the notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number string at the end of the metadata above, “190601-200918”, is the timestamp of the recording. I use that, in conjunction with the name of the speaker, as a way to uniquely name each audio file. When I transfer the files to my computer and organize them, I name them all with a common system to make them easy to search and identify. Each file is named with a language code, the time stamp, the name of the speaker, and a short description of the file contents.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;In the examples below, Tr1 marks the recordings from the headset mic, while TrLR marks the recordings from the recorder's onboard mic.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-10 center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;mx-auto d-block img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of files named with the schema defined above, for example 'SJTZ_190602-181041_MoisesGG_verb_paradigms_tam_Tr1.wav'&quot; title=&quot;If you can think of a better filenaming system... please just keep it to yourself? I have renamed my files enough already, thanks very much.&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/metadata/filenames.png&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Recordings in my &quot;SJTZ Verbs&quot; folder. I discuss some of this data in my post about &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/06/04/tlacochahuaya-zapotec-tam/&quot;&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec &quot;tense&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also keep a spreadsheet that catalogs all my files, and the metadata that is required to archive them. I archive my data at the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The AILLA website&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org&quot;&gt;Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America&lt;/a&gt; (AILLA), and they have a specific set of metadata fields you’re required to fill out, such as the length of the audio file and the role (e.g. researcher, speaker, or translator) of each person involved. My files in AILLA are also organized folders (called “Resources”) for different grammatical or cultural topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;mx-auto d-block img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;The spreadsheet headings include 'Entered by', 'File name, 'Media Type', 'Resource Name', and 'Media language 1'. The media type for each file is 'sound_recording', and the resource name is 'SJTZ Verbs'. The first media language is 'Zapotec, Western Tlacolula Valley'.&quot; title=&quot;If you can think of a better filenaming system... please just keep it to yourself? I have renamed my files enough already, thanks very much.&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/metadata/metadata-spreadsheet.png&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A small section of my very large metadata spreadsheet. You can read more about my archive collection &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/05/28/first-archive-deposit/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a lot of information to record at the end of each day, but it’s worth it to do it now! Last year I didn’t fully settle on a file-naming schema/organizational strategy until after I finished my fieldwork, and it caused a huge delay in archiving my data. Now that I have more practice, it all goes much more smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? Metadata is a very big topic, and people have lots of different ideas of what good metadata practice looks like. Here are a few starting points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America made a &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;AILLA's filenaming video on YouTube&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c-Mcp5ozgx0&quot;&gt;short video about how to name files&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;David Nathan and Peter K. Austin have written very good work about language documentation practices, and I recommend their article &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The article in volume 2 of Language Documentation and Description&quot; href=&quot;http://www.elpublishing.org/PID/029&quot;&gt;&quot;Reconceiving metadata: language documentation through thick and thin&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The Austin Principles website&quot; href=&quot;http://site.uit.no/linguisticsdatacitation/austinprinciples/&quot;&gt;Austin Principles of Data Citation in Linguistics&lt;/a&gt; outline several of the important factors in organizing and citing data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="archiving" /><category term="data-management" /><category term="fieldwork" /><category term="fieldwork2019" /><summary type="html">At the end of each day of fieldwork, I sit down and “deal with my data”. No matter how tired I am, no matter how much I want to put it off, it’s an essential part of my daily routine. The first thing I do is back up my recordings. And while my files are transferring, I go over my notes and make sure that all of my metadata is in order. Metadata is all the information about how the recording was made — who was there, where we were, what we talked about, what audio recorder I used, etc. Metadata is data about data, and it’s a crucial aspect of good data management.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Studying Tlacochahuaya Zapotec “tense”</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/04/tlacochahuaya-zapotec-tam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying Tlacochahuaya Zapotec &quot;tense&quot;" /><published>2019-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/04/tlacochahuaya-zapotec-tam</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/06/04/tlacochahuaya-zapotec-tam/">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-primary&quot; data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;#prelim-research&quot;&gt;Disclaimer: This is preliminary research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;collapse&quot; id=&quot;prelim-research&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p class=&quot;card card-body&quot; style=&quot;padding: 2mm; margin-bottom: 3mm;&quot;&gt;
				Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me.
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current focus of my research is “tense” in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec. That’s what I’ll be writing my &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;A paper you write to prove you’re ready to write a doctoral dissertation. In my department, it’s about the same length and rigor as a Master’s thesis.&quot;&gt;Qualifying Paper&lt;/a&gt; about next fall, and it’s the primary focus of my &lt;a title=&quot;Posts about my 2019 fieldwork&quot; href=&quot;/blog/tag/fieldwork2019/&quot;&gt;fieldwork this summer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put “tense” in quotes because what we colloquially call “tense”, linguists break down into three smaller categories: &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;The chronology of events. When something happened relative to a certain point in time. Did it happen yesterday? Three years ago? Is it going to happen tomorrow?&quot;&gt;tense&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Roughly, the state of the events progress — is it completed? in progress? ongoing? happening regularly? Some people call this the &amp;quot;shape&amp;quot; of the event.&quot;&gt;aspect&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;How real the event is. Is it something that definitely happened? Or something that was supposed to happen but didn't? Something that might happen? Something that will definitely happen tomorrow?&quot;&gt;mood&lt;/a&gt; (abbreviated together as TAM; click the words to get pop-up definitions).  These three categories are often very intertwined — it’s almost impossible to talk about one without the other two.  So what I’m actually researching right now is &lt;i&gt;TAM&lt;/i&gt; in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Most TAM markers in Zapotec languages are described as being primarily aspectual (having to do with aspect). But they also have implications about tense and mood.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In English, TAM can be marked with a suffix on the verb, as in &lt;i&gt;I dance&lt;/i&gt; vs. &lt;i&gt;I dance&lt;b&gt;d&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, where &lt;i&gt;-d&lt;/i&gt; marks the past tense. We also use auxiliary verbs, like the &lt;i&gt;will&lt;/i&gt; in &lt;i&gt;I &lt;b&gt;will&lt;/b&gt; dance&lt;/i&gt;. In Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, TAM is primarily indicated by a prefix on the verb, instead of a suffix.  For example, ‘Juan talks’ is &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;r&lt;/b&gt;ni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; with &lt;i&gt;r-&lt;/i&gt; at the beginning, while ‘Juan talked’ is &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;ni Jwan&lt;/i&gt; with a &lt;i&gt;b-&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;You might also notice that in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, the subject comes after the verb rather than before!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Each form has the same verb &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This is the part that encodes the actual meaning of the verb, 'talk'. We would hypothesize that the speaker stores the verb root in their memory, and constructs each form of the verb by applying rules about how TAM works.&quot;&gt;root&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;i&gt;ni&lt;/i&gt;, but with a different prefix. You can never use &lt;i&gt;ni&lt;/i&gt; on it’s own in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, it needs to have one of the TAM prefixes on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other Zapotec languages, verbs are divided into groups based on which TAM prefixes they use. These groups are called verb &lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;classes&lt;/span&gt;. We have something similar in English: some irregular verbs fall into patterns, like &lt;i&gt;sleep/slept&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;weep/wept&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;keep/kept&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;You can also have classes of other parts of speech. For example, Spanish has two noun classes, commonly called masculine (&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;el cielo&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; 'the sky') and feminine (&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;la biblioteca&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; 'the library').&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Based on related languages, I expect Tlacochahuaya Zapotec verbs to be divided into at least four (and possibly up to nine!) classes.  Identifying these classes is mostly a matter of learning lots of verbs and looking for patterns in their conjugation. I haven’t been able to clearly describe all of the classes yet, but I have noticed a few patterns.  As an example, I’ll just talk about three possible classes I’ve identified.  This is a super preliminary and somewhat simplified analysis, so please don’t quote me on it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this example, I’m just looking at two of the TAM prefixes, which for now I’ll call “past” and “future”.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;It is more complicated than this!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  In the Class 1 verbs, the past form has the prefix &lt;i&gt;b-&lt;/i&gt; and the future form has the prefix &lt;i&gt;i-&lt;/i&gt;. Easy! These prefixes are used for the verbs ‘ripen’ and ‘grow up’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;Verb Class 1&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;verb&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;past&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;future&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ga̰ts&lt;/i&gt; 'ripen'&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;ga̰ts&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;i&lt;/b&gt;ga̰ts&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ni'is&lt;/i&gt; 'grow up'&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;ni'is&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;i&lt;/b&gt;ni'is&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Class 2, the future still has the prefix &lt;i&gt;i-&lt;/i&gt;, but the past form is different. Instead of adding a prefix &lt;i&gt;b-&lt;/i&gt; like we did in Class 1, in these verbs we change the &lt;i&gt;k&lt;/i&gt; in the verb root to a &lt;i&gt;kw&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;So far, all the verbs in this group begin with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;k&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  This class includes the verbs ‘shiver’ and ‘borrow’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;Verb Class 2&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;verb&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;past&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;future&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;kanield&lt;/i&gt; 'shiver'&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;kw&lt;/b&gt;anield&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;i&lt;/b&gt;kanield&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;kala'&lt;/i&gt; 'borrow'&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;kw&lt;/b&gt;ala'&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;i&lt;/b&gt;kala'&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in Class 3, the past form has the prefix &lt;i&gt;b-&lt;/i&gt;, but also the &lt;i&gt;g&lt;/i&gt; in the verb root becomes a &lt;i&gt;d&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;So far, all the verbs in this group begin with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;g&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;   On top of that, in the future tense, there’s no &lt;i&gt;i-&lt;/i&gt;! Instead, the &lt;i&gt;g&lt;/i&gt; of the verb root becomes a &lt;i&gt;k&lt;/i&gt;. (Also, the future form has a higher tone than the past form.) In this class, we have the verbs ‘sew’ and ‘plant’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;Verb Class 3&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;th&gt;verb&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;past&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;&quot;future&quot;&lt;/th&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;gib&lt;/i&gt; 'sew'&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;bd&lt;/b&gt;ib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;k&lt;/b&gt;ib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;gix&lt;/i&gt; 'plant (a field)'&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This verb is used specifically when you're planting something that grows as a field, rather than in rows. For example, they use this verb to describe planting alfalfa and parsley.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;bd&lt;/b&gt;ix&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;k&lt;/b&gt;ix&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen some other patterns in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec verbs, but it would be too much to discuss here. Zapotec verb classes can be &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; complicated, but that makes them very exciting to study!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? There’s lots to know about verbs…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dr. Jeanette Sakel explains the difference between tense and aspect in &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;'Tense and aspect' on YouTube&quot; href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VM8GlP6avF4&quot;&gt;this short video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Gabriela Pérez Báez and Terrence Kaufman wrote about verb classes in Juchitán Zapotec. It was published in &lt;i&gt;Anthropological Linguistics&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Verb Classes in Juchitán Zapotec, available from Project Muse&quot; href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1353/anl.2016.0030&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For more about Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, you can check out the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Explore the Tlacochahuaya Zapotec Talking Dictionary&quot; href=&quot;http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/&quot;&gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec Talking Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;, or watch clips from &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Watch Dizhsa Nabani&quot; href=&quot;https://doculabs.haverford.edu/dizhsanabani/watch/&quot;&gt;Dizhsa Nabani&lt;/a&gt;, a documentary about language and daily life in Tlacochahuaya.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="mays-qualifying-paper" /><category term="tense-aspect-mood" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">Disclaimer: This is preliminary research Hello! Like many things I post on this blog, this research is in very early stages. This means that I may have simplified some more complicated details. It also means I might just be wrong! So please take this information as an early hypothesis, not a solid fact. If you'd like to find out my up-to-date opinions on the topic, feel free to email me. The current focus of my research is “tense” in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec. That’s what I’ll be writing my Qualifying Paper about next fall, and it’s the primary focus of my fieldwork this summer. I put “tense” in quotes because what we colloquially call “tense”, linguists break down into three smaller categories: tense, aspect, and mood (abbreviated together as TAM; click the words to get pop-up definitions). These three categories are often very intertwined — it’s almost impossible to talk about one without the other two. So what I’m actually researching right now is TAM in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What does a linguist do (in Oaxaca)?</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/30/what-does-a-linguist-do/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What does a linguist do (in Oaxaca)?" /><published>2019-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/30/what-does-a-linguist-do</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/30/what-does-a-linguist-do/">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Today I'm in Oaxaca City, Mexico.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Well, I drafted this in the Mexico City airport, but I'm revising it on the rooftop balcony of my hotel in Oaxaca City, where there's a lovely breeze, a view of the mountains, and a threat of rain.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Tomorrow I head to San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya, about 20 km east of the city, where I'll spend the next month learning about Tlacochahuaya Zapotec. Since I'm here, I thought I'd answer the question posed to me by every rideshare driver: &quot;You're a linguist? But, um, what do you do?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-12&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When linguists study language, they're seeking to understand (a) what constraints there are on how languages work, and (b) how any particular language fits into those constraints.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;First of all, that is not a completely comprehensive definition of linguistics, and second of all, neither of those questions is more important than the other!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Some linguists study how a speakers of a language produce and perceive sounds (&lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;phonetics&lt;/span&gt;), while others study how you order words in a sentence (&lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;syntax&lt;/span&gt;). Some linguists study how language shapes and interacts with identity (&lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;sociolinguistics&lt;/span&gt;), while others compare related languages to figure out what their ancestor language looked like thousands of years ago (&lt;span class=&quot;jargon&quot;&gt;historical linguistics&lt;/span&gt;).  And of course, you can study the linguistics of any language! Mandarin, English, Portuguese, Xhosa, or any of the other &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Linguistic Society of America page on linguistic diversity&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linguisticsociety.org/content/how-many-languages-are-there-world&quot;&gt;nearly 7,000 thousand languages&lt;/a&gt; are available.  By looking at different languages from around the world, we can build a better understanding of how the human ability for language works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-7 center&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img alt=&quot;map of the Tlacolula Valley&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/what-does-a-linguist-do/tlacolula-valley.png&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Map of the Tlacolula Valley. I spend most of my time in San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya, marked in blue in the middle of the map.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;This map is from a book called &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Oaxaca: Distritos, Limites, Caminos, Municipios, y Localidades&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;, published by Angel García García y Asociados, S.C. It has maps of different parts of Oaxaca, as well as census data for all the towns. Last I tried, you could buy a copy at Priv. De Rayón No. 104, Centro, Oax. 68000. Or &amp;lt;a href='mailto:mayhplumb@utexas.edu'&amp;gt;email me&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; if you'd like a scan of something. :)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past several years, my research has focused on a language called Valley Zapotec.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;More precisely I study Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec, but that is a very long name, and that amount of detail isn't necessary here.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This language is spoken in the Tlacolula Valley, which stretches between Oaxaca City and Tlacolula de Matamoros. But while I call Valley Zapotec a “language”, in reality, every town in the Valley speaks a distinct variety.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Linguists call this region a 'dialect continuum' or a 'dialect chain'.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  The &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Informally, this is how 'healthy' the language is. While the primary factor in language vitality is the number of children who are learning the language, language vitality is also determined by things like how many contexts the language is used in (e.g. in the home, in school, in government), how much pressure there is from outside languages, and how the language is perceived.&quot;&gt;language vitality&lt;/a&gt; also varies from town to town. In San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya, where I have worked the most, children no longer speak the language, and the youngest fluent speaker is in his 40s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I’m in Tlacochahuaya, what will I actually be doing? In order to study Tlacochahuaya Zapotec grammar, I need to record examples of people using the language. This can be as simple as asking people to translate sentences, but it’s also important to collect examples of “natural” language. I frequently ask people to tell me stories in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, or to describe activities and customs (for example, I have recordings of people telling me about &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;How to plant garlic (AntonioGC)&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:262660&quot;&gt;how to plant garlic&lt;/a&gt; and about &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;All Saints Day celebrations (JoseAM)&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:262620&quot;&gt;All Saints’ Day celebrations&lt;/a&gt;). I then go through the recording sentence by sentence with one of my teachers to translate it into Spanish or English. By comparing data across many recordings, I can identify larger patterns in the language’s grammar that I would never be able to see in individual sentences.  This summer, I’m particularly interested in studying verb tenses — I’ll write about that some time!&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;It's... a bit more complicated than just 'tense'.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Disclaimer: this is what &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; do. Linguists do &lt;i&gt;all sorts of things&lt;/i&gt;, and even other linguists focusing on language documentation will have different priorities and methods than I do.  But in general, this is how linguistic fieldwork happens.]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="fieldwork2019" /><category term="fieldwork" /><category term="language-documentation" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">Today I'm in Oaxaca City, Mexico. Tomorrow I head to San Jerónimo Tlacochahuaya, about 20 km east of the city, where I'll spend the next month learning about Tlacochahuaya Zapotec. Since I'm here, I thought I'd answer the question posed to me by every rideshare driver: &quot;You're a linguist? But, um, what do you do?&quot; When linguists study language, they're seeking to understand (a) what constraints there are on how languages work, and (b) how any particular language fits into those constraints.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first blog post / My first archive deposit</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/28/first-archive-deposit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first blog post / My first archive deposit" /><published>2019-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/28/first-archive-deposit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/28/first-archive-deposit/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the blog! I’m using my inaugural post to mark a momentous occasion. It is with great pride that I announce &lt;i&gt;*drumroll*&lt;/i&gt; my very first archive deposit!  I’ll go into more detail below, but if you want to skip ahead, you can check out my archive collection &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Zapotec Collection of May Helena Plumb&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:257460&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer (2018), I spent five weeks in San Jéronimo Tlacochahuaya (Oaxaca, Mexico) learning about the Zapotec language they speak there.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec is also spoken in in diaspora communities in the United States.  It's a beautiful language. If you don't want to sift through my archive deposit, you can check out the &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='Explore the Tlacochahuaya Zapotec Talking Dictionary' href='http://talkingdictionary.swarthmore.edu/tlacochahuaya/'&amp;gt;Tlacochahuaya Zapotec Talking Dictionary&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, or watch clips from &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='Watch Dizhsa Nabani' href='https://doculabs.haverford.edu/dizhsanabani/watch/'&amp;gt;Dizhsa Nabani&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, a documentary about language and daily life in Tlacochahuaya.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I came home with lots of recordings, data which will be the foundation of my future research on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec grammar.&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;  These recordings aren’t just useful to me, though, they’re important for anyone who wants to learn about Zapotec (or anyone who wants to evaluate my claims).  So I put them in an &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Broadly speaking, an archive is a collection of objects that have been organized, cataloged, and otherwise prepared for long-term preservation. Archives are similar to museums, except that while museum curation focuses on the display of objects, archiving focuses on the permanent preservation of the objects.  If you want to learn more about archives, I recommend &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://youtu.be/QNN2LFe_iD8'&amp;gt;this video from the Tate&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;, where anyone can access them. I chose the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;AILLA homepage&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/&quot;&gt;Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America&lt;/a&gt; (AILLA), which is hosted at the University of Texas.  All of my recordings are publicly available. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Zapotec Collection of May Helena Plumb&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:257460&quot;&gt;You could go listen to them!&lt;/a&gt; (All you need to do is &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;AILLA registration page&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/user/register&quot;&gt;create a free AILLA account&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll continue to add to my archive collection as my research progresses, but for now, there are 29 resources (63 total files).  Some of these resources are short texts in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec, such as a session where Antonio García Cruz talked to me about &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;About donkeys (AntonioGC)&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:262614&quot;&gt;how smart donkeys are&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Donkeys are very good at remembering routes and finding their way home, and they can navigate down craggy slopes very gently while carrying a heavy load.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Other resources focus on particular words and phrases, such as my conversations with Moisés García Guzmán about &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Funerals in SJT (MoisesGG)&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ailla.utexas.org/islandora/object/ailla:262635&quot;&gt;ritual speech at Tlacochahuaya funerals&lt;/a&gt;. Right now, most of the resources contain audio recordings in Tlacochahuaya Zapotec and Spanish,&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Many of my conversations with Moisés are in English, though, so if you don't speak Spanish those are good resources to check out.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but in the future, I’ll add transcriptions and translations of the Zapotec audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This archive deposit has been a full year in the making,&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Yeah, it took a long time. I’ll write about why in a future post, probably.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s an exciting step in my research process. As I said above, putting my data in an archive means that other people can access it, which is an important part of responsible scholarship.  But why an archive and not just a personal website? Because AILLA will store my data longterm, making sure the recordings are safeguarded against &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;Over time, things break down. Ink fades, cassette tapes desitegrate, and the bits that make up your audio files can get altered by small failures in the storage system.&quot;&gt;data decay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;As technology advanced, some file and storage formats become unreadable. Most people don't have an easy way to read a floppy disk, for example, and some old Microsoft Works documents can't be opened in a modern text editor.&quot;&gt;digital obscelence&lt;/a&gt;. This means that in the future, when Tlacochahuaya Zapotec changes (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Linguistics Society of America page on language change&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linguisticsociety.org/content/english-changing&quot;&gt;as all languages do&lt;/a&gt;) or if it &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Article on language endangerment from the Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Linguistics&quot; href=&quot;https://dx.doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780199384655.013.21&quot;&gt;ceases to be spoken&lt;/a&gt;, we will still have a record of how it was spoken in 2018. Maintaining data is a lot of work, so to close, I’d like to thank the lovely folks at AILLA for their help setting up my collection. Give your archivist a (consensual) hug today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know more? Here are some more resources about archiving:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;the video on Youtube&quot; href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fst-KczfG-4&quot;&gt;this short video&lt;/a&gt; about AILLA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;David Nathan's article &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.elpublishing.org/PID/085&quot;&gt;&quot;Language documentation and archiving: from disk space to MySpace&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;other language archives, such as &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;ELAR homepage&quot; href=&quot;https://elar.soas.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;Endangered Languages Archive&lt;/a&gt; (ELAR) and &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;TLA homepage&quot; href=&quot;https://tla.mpi.nl/&quot;&gt;The Language Archive&lt;/a&gt; (TLA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="archiving" /><category term="data-management" /><category term="zapotec" /><summary type="html">Welcome to the blog! I’m using my inaugural post to mark a momentous occasion. It is with great pride that I announce *drumroll* my very first archive deposit! I’ll go into more detail below, but if you want to skip ahead, you can check out my archive collection here. Last summer (2018), I spent five weeks in San Jéronimo Tlacochahuaya (Oaxaca, Mexico) learning about the Zapotec language they speak there. I came home with lots of recordings, data which will be the foundation of my future research on Tlacochahuaya Zapotec grammar.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is an (embroidered) wug?</title><link href="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/27/what-is-a-wug/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is an (embroidered) wug?" /><published>2019-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/27/what-is-a-wug</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mayhplumb.com/blog/2019/05/27/what-is-a-wug/">&lt;p&gt;The short answer is, this is a wug:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-6 col-sm-6 col-md-4 col-lg-2 center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;mx-auto d-block img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;A blue bird drawn in a simple cartoon style.&quot; title=&quot;This is a wug.&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/what-is-a-wug/this-is-a-wug.png&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wug was invented by linguist Jean Berko Gleason&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;I took a selfie with her once. &amp;lt;img width='200px' src='/blog/img/what-is-a-wug/selfie-with-jean.jpg'/&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as part of a language acquisition experiment. Gleason wanted to find out when children learned to make English plurals.  So she drew small creatures with made-up names, like the wug, and set up a task where children were prompted to say plural forms of the words. The prompt looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col col-sm-9 col-md-6 col-lg-4 center&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;mx-auto d-block img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;A drawing of a bird is followed by the text 'This is a wug'. Two more birds are followed by the text 'Now there is another one. There are two of them. There are two _'&quot; title=&quot;If you have a high-quality image of one of the other animals, let me know.&quot; src=&quot;/blog/img/what-is-a-wug/this-is-a-wug-test.png&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English plural of &lt;i&gt;wug&lt;/i&gt; would be pronounced with a [z] sound on the end, [wʌgz].  If children produce this form, it means they’ve learned a general rule about creating English plurals, rather than simply memorizing the singular and plural of each noun. Gleason found that most preschoolers know how to make this plural (76%), and that almost all children aquire it by around age six (97% of first-graders).  She published these results in an 1958 article “The Child’s Learning of English Morphology”.&lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; data-content=&quot;The offical article is &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='official page at Taylor &amp;amp; Francis' href='https://doi.org/10.1080/00437956.1958.11659661'&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.  There's currently a free PDF &amp;lt;a target='_blank' title='PDF from Western University' href='https://anthropology.uwo.ca/faculty/creider/027/wugs.pdf'&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wugs are just so cute, they became the unoffical mascot of linguistics.  You’ll find them on mugs and t-shirts, and I embroidered one in the center of my animal-themed English vowel chart (for the &lt;a tabindex=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;jargon&quot; data-toggle=&quot;popover&quot; title=&quot;International Phonetic Alphabet&quot; data-content=&quot;The IPA is a standardized system where every speech sound is assigned a unique symbol. &amp;lt;a target='_blank' href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Phonetic_Alphabet'&amp;gt;Wikipedia&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; is a good starting place to learn more.&quot;&gt;IPA&lt;/a&gt; vowel [ʌ]).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Yeah sure I started grad school and resubmitted a journal article but my proudest accomplishment of 2017 is this embroidered English vowel chart &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/d78m8KADHm&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/d78m8KADHm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; May Helena Plumb (@mayhplumb) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mayhplumb/status/938551826386911233?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 6, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to learn more? Wugs are all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;watch the video on YouTube&quot; href=&quot;https://youtu.be/1Lb6phcDte4&quot;&gt;&quot;The Wug Test&quot;&lt;/a&gt; by The Ling Space&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;the podcast transcript&quot; href=&quot;https://lingthusiasm.com/post/170650662718/transcript-lingthusiasm-episode-16-learning-parts&quot;&gt;&quot;Learning parts of words -  Morphemes and the wug test&quot;&lt;/a&gt; by Lingthusiasm&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;PDF on Google Drive&quot; href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B0tzldu_jPd2WUdhMlc5SFFVX0JkZmpCdjdfTk1nMGpGcU9F/&quot;&gt;Wug crochet pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;a wug meme on All Things Linguistic&quot; href=&quot;https://allthingslinguistic.com/post/179126032052/allthingslinguistic-when-two-wugs-love-each-other&quot;&gt;When it all gets out of hand...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>mayhplumb</name></author><category term="wugs" /><category term="crafty-linguistics" /><category term="language-acquisition" /><summary type="html">The short answer is, this is a wug:</summary></entry></feed>